<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>automation on Andrea Dainese</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/categories/automation/</link><description>Recent content in automation on Andrea Dainese</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.adainese.it/categories/automation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A practical Cisco NDO multi-site use case: config deploy</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/30/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-config-deploy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/30/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-config-deploy/</guid><description>At this stage, we can build the configuration:
./build-nac-data.py If everything runs successfully, the script completes silently (&amp;ldquo;no news is good news&amp;rdquo;), creating or updating files under nac-data and site-* directories.</description></item><item><title>A practical Cisco NDO multi-site use case: building the parser</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/23/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-building-the-parser/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/23/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-building-the-parser/</guid><description>The parser is a custom script that converts user input (via CSV files) into NaC configuration. It also performs data validation, as described in the previous post. If successful, the parser generates NaC files within the nac-data directory, these are then consumed by Terraform to configure NDO and APIC.</description></item><item><title>EVE-NG (SW architecture and docker support)</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/22/eve-ng-sw-architecture-and-docker-support/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/22/eve-ng-sw-architecture-and-docker-support/</guid><description>Special thanks to Carlo Cianfarani for providing this post.
Continue reading the post on Patreon .</description></item><item><title>A practical Cisco NDO multi-site use case: data validation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/16/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-data-validation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/16/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-data-validation/</guid><description>As we&amp;rsquo;ve seen, CSV files are used to generate the NaC configuration. However, it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to perform validation tests to ensure correctness.
Starting with the CSV file defining networks:
VLAN_ID must contain an integer within a defined VLAN pool.</description></item><item><title>A practical Cisco NDO multi-site use case: additional configuration</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/09/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-additional-configuration/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/09/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-additional-configuration/</guid><description>In the previous article, we built the data structure that defines our infrastructure and most of its operational logic. However, there are some elements that require a different handling approach.</description></item><item><title>A practical Cisco NDO multi-site use case: modelling</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/02/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-modelling/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/11/02/a-practical-cisco-ndo-multi-site-use-case-modelling/</guid><description>The example presented here covers the deployment of a multi-site fabric managed through NDO. The current setup, based on a legacy environment, must be migrated to a newly implemented multi-site environment.</description></item><item><title>Managing Cisco NDO Limitations from the APIC</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/26/managing-cisco-ndo-limitations-from-the-apic/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/26/managing-cisco-ndo-limitations-from-the-apic/</guid><description>We have observed that NDO currently has some important limitations that must be kept in mind:
NDO frameworks have limitations, particularly NaC NDO itself has limitations certain configurations must necessarily be managed directly on the APIC This consideration is far from trivial, and to fully understand it, we need to analyze how objects are created by NDO on the APIC.</description></item><item><title>Simplifying the Data Structure</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/19/simplifying-the-data-structure/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/19/simplifying-the-data-structure/</guid><description>In all the automation projects I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on, the operations teams usually don&amp;rsquo;t have the skills needed to effectively manage the automation framework itself.
In other words, the data structures behind Ansible, Terraform, and NaC are often too complex for operations teams to handle directly.</description></item><item><title>Frameworks for Projects with Cisco ACI and NDO</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/12/frameworks-for-projects-with-cisco-aci-and-ndo/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/12/frameworks-for-projects-with-cisco-aci-and-ndo/</guid><description>When developing an automation system for Cisco ACI and NDO, we have several frameworks to choose from:
APIs: maximum flexibility, but requiring significant effort and strong programming skills.
APIC: API-first approach, with documentation available directly through the Web UI.</description></item><item><title>Creating an interface in Strata Cloud Manager</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/05/creating-an-interface-in-strata-cloud-manager/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/05/creating-an-interface-in-strata-cloud-manager/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the final relevant example: creating a new interface.
To create an interface, we use the POST method and provide the correct data structure. The challenge, however, is determining what that structure should look like.</description></item><item><title>Circular Dependencies with NDO</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/01/circular-dependencies-with-ndo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/10/01/circular-dependencies-with-ndo/</guid><description>We already highlighted how critical the design phase is in any automation project. This is even more true when working with NDO, since a design mistake could easily compromise the entire project.</description></item><item><title>Modifying an object in Strata Cloud Manager</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/28/modifying-an-object-in-strata-cloud-manager/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/28/modifying-an-object-in-strata-cloud-manager/</guid><description>This example is particularly relevant because it directly impacts operational workflows.
Before diving into the example, let&amp;rsquo;s review the HTTP methods used in REST APIs. HTTP defines five default methods that map to CRUD operations: Create, Read, Update, Delete:</description></item><item><title>From Single-Site to Multi-Site with NDO</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/24/from-single-site-to-multi-site-with-ndo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/24/from-single-site-to-multi-site-with-ndo/</guid><description>As infrastructures expand across different geographic locations and distances grow larger, moving from a single-site setup to a multi-site architecture becomes a natural step.
In an ideal world, each site in a multi-site deployment should operate independently.</description></item><item><title>Retrieving firewall interfaces with Strata Cloud Manager</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/21/retrieving-firewall-interfaces-with-strata-cloud-manager/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/21/retrieving-firewall-interfaces-with-strata-cloud-manager/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a second example that illustrates both the functionality and the complexity of SCM&amp;rsquo;s APIs.
In this scenario, we want to retrieve the Ethernet interfaces of the firewalls. A quick search in the documentation leads us to the correct API endpoint .</description></item><item><title>EVE-NG Linux VM SSH troubleshooting</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/20/eve-ng-linux-vm-ssh-troubleshooting/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/20/eve-ng-linux-vm-ssh-troubleshooting/</guid><description>Special thanks to Carlo Cianfarani for providing this post.
In this post we will explore how to troubleshoot and fix an issue on EVE-NG involving Linux VMs connected through a virtual router instance (Cisco XRd) implemented as docker container.</description></item><item><title>Optimizing Strata Cloud Manager API usage</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/14/optimizing-strata-cloud-manager-api-usage/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/14/optimizing-strata-cloud-manager-api-usage/</guid><description>Before moving forward, let&amp;rsquo;s review our current approach to invoking the API:
We are using the requests library. We must first generate an authentication token. Many parameters are repeatedly passed in multiple calls.</description></item><item><title>Authenticating to the Strata Cloud Manager API</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/07/authenticating-to-the-strata-cloud-manager-api/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/07/authenticating-to-the-strata-cloud-manager-api/</guid><description>According to the official documentation , before making any API calls, you must first obtain an access token using your username, password, and tenant service group.
This token can then be used to authorize subsequent API requests.</description></item><item><title>Logging into Cisco ACI</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/03/logging-into-cisco-aci/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/09/03/logging-into-cisco-aci/</guid><description>Before proceeding, we need one more piece of information: how Cisco ACI handles authentication.
The documentation indicates that we can authenticate to the APIC via a POST request to /api/aaaLogin.json. The request body must include the username and password inside a JSON object:</description></item><item><title>Automating operations with Strata Cloud Manager</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/31/automating-operations-with-strata-cloud-manager/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/31/automating-operations-with-strata-cloud-manager/</guid><description>Management of Palo Alto Networks firewalls is gradually shifting from traditional on-premises administration, either directly or via Panorama , to a cloud-based model. The product enabling centralized, cloud-based management of Palo Alto Networks firewall infrastructures is Strata Cloud Manager (SCM) .</description></item><item><title>Cisco ACI object model explained</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/27/cisco-aci-object-model-explained/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/27/cisco-aci-object-model-explained/</guid><description>Before diving into the Cisco ACI APIs, we need a brief introduction to the hierarchical structure of its elements.
This article may look intimidating due to its complexity. In reality, it should be used as a reference whenever we need to better understand a detail in order to optimize our automation.</description></item><item><title>Operating with Cisco ACI</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/24/operating-with-cisco-aci/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/24/operating-with-cisco-aci/</guid><description>Cisco ACI can be managed through five different interfaces:
GUI: The graphical user interface, typically used for the initial setup and, unfortunately, often still used for direct day-to-day operations on the fabric.</description></item><item><title>Setting up a Cisco ACI lab environment</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/17/setting-up-a-cisco-aci-lab-environment/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/17/setting-up-a-cisco-aci-lab-environment/</guid><description>Before diving into the technical aspects, it&amp;rsquo;s essential to prepare a dedicated environment for testing and development. Under no circumstances should integrations be tested directly on production systems. A safe, isolated environment is required.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Cisco ACI</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/10/introduction-to-cisco-aci/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/10/introduction-to-cisco-aci/</guid><description>Cisco ACI is Cisco&amp;rsquo;s Software-Defined Networking (SDN) solution specifically designed for data center networking. I would argue that it is Cisco&amp;rsquo;s only truly SDN-native solution, as it was built from the ground up to be API-first.</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting EVE-NG nodes that fail to start</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/03/troubleshooting-eve-ng-nodes-that-fail-to-start/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/08/03/troubleshooting-eve-ng-nodes-that-fail-to-start/</guid><description>In this article, we will explore how to troubleshoot EVE-NG nodes that fail to start properly. The symptom is straightforward yet frustrating: when attempting to start a node, it appears to launch but then shuts down after a few seconds without any explanation.</description></item><item><title>Developing UNetLab v3 with AI (LLM)</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/07/27/developing-unetlab-v3-with-ai-llm/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/07/27/developing-unetlab-v3-with-ai-llm/</guid><description>UNetLab v3 is built on Django along with various other frameworks. I am not a professional developer, nor do I consider myself one, yet I&amp;rsquo;m often told that my prototypes are extremely useful, especially because I can build them in very short timeframes.</description></item><item><title>Automating Palo Alto Firewall via Python PAN SDK</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/07/12/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-python-pan-sdk/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/07/12/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-python-pan-sdk/</guid><description>In the previous post, we explored the official pan-os-python library maintained by Palo Alto Networks. We also noted that this library builds upon the personal work of Kevin Steves, who developed the pan-python library, enabling low-level operations on PAN-OS systems.</description></item><item><title>Automating Palo Alto Firewall via Python PAN-OS SDK</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/07/05/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-python-pan-os-sdk/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/07/05/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-python-pan-os-sdk/</guid><description>In previous posts, we explored how to automate certain operations on Palo Alto Networks firewalls using XML API and REST API directly. According to the official documentation , there are ready-to-use libraries available for several programming languages (PHP, Go, Python).</description></item><item><title>Automating Palo Alto Firewall via REST API</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/28/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-rest-api/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/28/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-rest-api/</guid><description>Palo Alto Networks firewalls were originally designed around XML APIs. JSON-based REST APIs were introduced later and, as a result, the implementation is currently incomplete and, as we&amp;rsquo;ll see, prone to certain errors.</description></item><item><title>Automating Palo Alto Firewall via XML API</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/21/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-xml-api/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/21/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-xml-api/</guid><description>Palo Alto Networks firewalls provide XML-based APIs for interacting with the system. To use the API, the first step is to generate an API key that will authenticate our requests:</description></item><item><title>Automating Palo Alto Firewall via CLI</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/14/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-cli/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/14/automating-palo-alto-firewall-via-cli/</guid><description>The first method we will discuss is called screen scraping, a topic already covered in the past. We use the screen scraping approach when automating devices that are designed to be managed via CLI, without APIs that allow us to cover all the scenarios we are interested in.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Palo Alto firewall automation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/07/introduction-to-palo-alto-firewall-automation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/06/07/introduction-to-palo-alto-firewall-automation/</guid><description>The automation of firewalls is still a relatively under-discussed topic compared to the automation of network devices. This is likely due to complexity: firewall policies tend to be a long list of rules, created by different people, for different (application) purposes, and aggregated together.</description></item><item><title>TextFSM: parsing non-tabular text</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/31/textfsm-parsing-non-tabular-text/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/31/textfsm-parsing-non-tabular-text/</guid><description>Many network devices provide two commands to retrieve specific information: the first command returns a summarized output in tabular format, while the second command provides a more detailed view, typically in a non-tabular format where each entry is separated into a specific section.</description></item><item><title>Consuming MISP IoCs from a Firewall</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/24/consuming-misp-iocs-from-a-firewall/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/24/consuming-misp-iocs-from-a-firewall/</guid><description>Once our MISP instance is properly configured, it contains a set of threat intelligence data that can be leveraged by prevention tools such as Firewalls, Email Gateways, and more.
Let&amp;rsquo;s explore how to extract IoCs from MISP.</description></item><item><title>TextFSM: parsing tabular text</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/17/textfsm-parsing-tabular-text/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/17/textfsm-parsing-tabular-text/</guid><description>In the previous post, we discussed how to structure the output of the show interfaces command. Now, for educational purposes, let&amp;rsquo;s examine how to structure the equivalent command that returns output in tabular format: show interfaces status.</description></item><item><title>Parsing text with TextFSM</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/10/parsing-text-with-textfsm/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/10/parsing-text-with-textfsm/</guid><description>TextFSM is a framework developed by Google that enables the transformation (parsing) of human-readable text into structured, machine-readable output.
TextFSM, available as a Python module, is one of the essential tools when automating a network device that requires CLI interaction, allowing us to interpret the output in order to make decisions.</description></item><item><title>Installing MISP</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/06/installing-misp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/06/installing-misp/</guid><description>Installing MISP is relatively straightforward and is well documented in the user guide . For some reason, the user guide does not yet mention Ubuntu 24.04, although the installation script is available in the repository.</description></item><item><title>Integrating and automating MISP</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/04/integrating-and-automating-misp/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/04/integrating-and-automating-misp/</guid><description>MISP is a platform for threat intelligence, not for incident management. Specifically, MISP helps manage Indicators of Compromise (IoCs) in a structured way, and therefore it must be integrated into an existing ecosystem.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to MISP</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/04/introduction-to-misp/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/04/introduction-to-misp/</guid><description>MISP (Malware Information Sharing Platform) is an open-source software solution for collecting, storing, distributing, and sharing cybersecurity indicators and threat intelligence related to cybersecurity incident analysis and malware analysis. MISP is designed for incident analysts, security professionals, ICT specialists, and malware reverse engineers to support their daily operations and efficiently share structured information.</description></item><item><title>Threat Intelligence automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/04/threat-intelligence-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/04/threat-intelligence-automation-series/</guid><description>In today&amp;rsquo;s fast-paced digital world, manually tracking and responding to cybersecurity threats is no longer enough. Automating threat intelligence helps organizations stay one step ahead by streamlining detection, analysis, and response.</description></item><item><title>Writing presentations with Markdown</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/03/writing-presentations-with-markdown/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/05/03/writing-presentations-with-markdown/</guid><description>Previously, we discussed improving documentation management by focusing on content rather than tools. Specifically, we explored how high-quality documents can be generated using Markdown , CSS, and WeasyPrint .
When it comes to documents, optimization is not just about streamlining content writing but also about automating parts of the process.</description></item><item><title>Industrial network segmentation with Private VLANs</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/30/industrial-network-segmentation-with-private-vlans/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/30/industrial-network-segmentation-with-private-vlans/</guid><description>We have explored how to transparently segment an OT/ICS network into groups using VLAN Insertion from Palo Alto Networks. The flexibility of this feature has allowed us to divide our lab environments into groups without the need to reconfigure IP addresses.</description></item><item><title>Attacking the Chemical plant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/23/attacking-the-chemical-plant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/23/attacking-the-chemical-plant/</guid><description>Compared to VirtuaPlant, this scenario is more complex and allows us to explore potential attacks on a PLC in greater detail.
Reconnaissance Phase As done previously, we analyze the holding and coil registers:</description></item><item><title>Event-Driven Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/19/event-driven-ansible/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/19/event-driven-ansible/</guid><description>Event-Driven Ansible (EDA) allows the execution of an Ansible playbook to be triggered by a specific event.
This capability exponentially increases Ansible&amp;rsquo;s potential, transforming it into a tool for automating processes based on specific events, such as troubleshooting, threat intelligence, IoCs, data collection, and general analysis.</description></item><item><title>Installing the GRFICSv2 Chemical plant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/16/installing-the-grficsv2-chemical-plant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/16/installing-the-grficsv2-chemical-plant/</guid><description>As we have seen, the GRFICSv2 simulator consists of four main components: HMI, PLC, Simulator, and EWS.
In a real-world ICS environment, the HMI, PLC, and Simulator are connected to the field network, where a gateway facilitates communication between the OT network and the field devices.</description></item><item><title>Delegate Ansible tasks to a different host</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/12/delegate-ansible-tasks-to-a-different-host/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/12/delegate-ansible-tasks-to-a-different-host/</guid><description>By default, Ansible executes playbooks on a single host. However, in various scenarios, tasks need to be executed across multiple hosts in a specific sequence. A common example is a web server that must be taken offline from the load balancer before being modified.</description></item><item><title>An ICS lab with GRFICSv2</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/09/an-ics-lab-with-grficsv2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/09/an-ics-lab-with-grficsv2/</guid><description>GRFICSv2 (Graphical Realism Framework for Industrial Control Simulations) is an Industrial Control Systems (ICS) simulator developed by Fortiphyd and released in 2020. Unlike VirtuaPlant, GRFICSv2 integrates an HMI, a PLC, and a simulation environment.</description></item><item><title>Reboot a device with Ansible and wait for it to come online</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/05/reboot-a-device-with-ansible-and-wait-for-it-to-come-online/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/05/reboot-a-device-with-ansible-and-wait-for-it-to-come-online/</guid><description>A more complex interactive task than those seen before is rebooting the device and waiting for it to be available again. Although Ansible is not designed specifically for this purpose, it can be useful, for example, in a procedure that updates device firmware.</description></item><item><title>Industrial network segmentation with VLAN Insertion</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/02/industrial-network-segmentation-with-vlan-insertion/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/04/02/industrial-network-segmentation-with-vlan-insertion/</guid><description>In real-world industrial environments, it is common to have all OT/ICS devices configured with IP addresses belonging to a single large network. This setup allows different production lines or plants to potentially communicate without any filtering.</description></item><item><title>Attacking the Oil Refinery plant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/26/attacking-the-oil-refinery-plant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/26/attacking-the-oil-refinery-plant/</guid><description>We have already explored how to attack the Bottle Filling system. This article follows up on that analysis but in a significantly more complex scenario.
Reconnaissance phase The Bottle Filling system operated automatically.</description></item><item><title>Orchestrating playbooks with Ansible AWX</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/22/orchestrating-playbooks-with-ansible-awx/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/22/orchestrating-playbooks-with-ansible-awx/</guid><description>Ansible AWX is the open-source version from which Ansible Tower draws inspiration. Both AWX and Tower are orchestrators for Ansible playbook
Ansible AWX is the open-source version from which Ansible Tower draws inspiration.</description></item><item><title>Installing VirtuaPlant Oil Refinery plant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/19/installing-virtuaplant-oil-refinery-plant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/19/installing-virtuaplant-oil-refinery-plant/</guid><description>Originally, VirtuaPlant included only one scenario, but later, an external contributor ( GitHub user prjpet ) added an additional scenario, further expanding its capabilities.
he simulation and HMI communicate using the Modbus protocol.</description></item><item><title>Ansible Galaxy</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/16/ansible-galaxy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/16/ansible-galaxy/</guid><description>Ansible provides Galaxy, which allows managing packages containing roles and collections. Roles and collections can be directly referenced by Ansible playbooks. Galaxy enables the use of packages published directly on the public portal but also allows managing private repositories.</description></item><item><title>Attacking the Bottle Filling plant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/12/attacking-the-bottle-filling-plant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/12/attacking-the-bottle-filling-plant/</guid><description>This scenario serves as an introduction to attacking a Modbus-based PLC. The goal is to gradually understand the system&amp;rsquo;s behavior by monitoring the PLC registers before executing an attack.
Reconnaissance phase Before launching an attack, it is crucial to analyze the plant&amp;rsquo;s behavior.</description></item><item><title>Ansible reporting with ARA</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/09/ansible-reporting-with-ara/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/09/ansible-reporting-with-ara/</guid><description>ARA Records Ansible provides a simple dashboard to visualize the execution of Ansible playbooks. It is not an orchestration tool but rather
ARA Records Ansible provides a simple dashboard to visualize the execution of Ansible playbooks.</description></item><item><title>Installing VirtuaPlant Bottle Filling plant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/05/installing-virtuaplant-bottle-filling-plant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/05/installing-virtuaplant-bottle-filling-plant/</guid><description>The first scenario available in VirtuaPlant simulates a basic bottle-filling plant. This scenario includes a graphical Human-Machine Interface (HMI) that allows users to interact with the simulated industrial process.
The simulation and HMI communicate using the Modbus protocol.</description></item><item><title>EVE-NG network interfaces explained</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/02/eve-ng-network-interfaces-explained/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/02/eve-ng-network-interfaces-explained/</guid><description>The network infrastructure that EVE-NG uses to interconnect lab nodes is somewhat obscure. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore how to identify the Linux interfaces of each virtualized node for debugging or simple analysis.</description></item><item><title>Managing CLI prompts with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/01/managing-cli-prompts-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/03/01/managing-cli-prompts-with-ansible/</guid><description>Some commands, before becoming operational, ask for confirmation from the operator. Ansible has a basic capability to handle these situations thanks to the cli_command and ios_command modules. The first one is generic, the second one is specific to Cisco IOS systems, but both essentially perform the same function with some peculiarities and limitations.</description></item><item><title>An ICS lab with VirtuaPlant</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/26/an-ics-lab-with-virtuaplant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/26/an-ics-lab-with-virtuaplant/</guid><description>VirtuaPlant is an Industrial Control Systems (ICS) simulator developed by Jan Seidl in 2015. Unlike most PLC simulators, which only allow reading and writing tags, VirtuaPlant introduces real-world-like control logic, making it a more advanced and interactive learning tool.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Modbus protocol</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/19/introduction-to-modbus-protocol/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/19/introduction-to-modbus-protocol/</guid><description>Modbus is a widely used industrial communication protocol originally developed by Modicon (now part of Schneider Electric) in 1979. It is open, royalty-free, and simple to implement, making it one of the most popular protocols for connecting Programmable Logic Controllers (PLCs), Remote Terminal Units (RTUs), sensors, and other industrial devices.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to OT/ICS</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/12/introduction-to-ot/ics/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/12/introduction-to-ot/ics/</guid><description>Operational Technology (OT) encompasses the systems responsible for monitoring and controlling industrial operations. Within OT, **Industrial Control Systems (ICS)** refer specifically to technologies used for automating and managing industrial processes.</description></item><item><title>Simplifying documentation with Markdown and CI/CD</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/05/simplifying-documentation-with-markdown-and-ci/cd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/02/05/simplifying-documentation-with-markdown-and-ci/cd/</guid><description>In every company I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered, documentation is a recurring challenge. It&amp;rsquo;s a complex topic: creating documentation is labor-intensive, but keeping it up to date is even more demanding. This often leads to outdated or non-existent documentation.</description></item><item><title>OT/ICS series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/29/ot/ics-series/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/29/ot/ics-series/</guid><description>In today&amp;rsquo;s interconnected world, securing and understanding Operational Technology (OT) and Industrial Control Systems (ICS) is more important than ever. This series of posts explores hands-on lab setups, security best practices, and key learning resources to help you build, test, and protect critical infrastructure.</description></item><item><title>Why build an OT/ICS Cybersecurity lab?</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/29/why-build-an-ot/ics-cybersecurity-lab/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/29/why-build-an-ot/ics-cybersecurity-lab/</guid><description>For several years now, I have been deeply interested in the security challenges of Industrial Control Systems (ICS) and Operational Technology (OT). Living in a region renowned for its manufacturing excellence, many of my clients operate in this domain.</description></item><item><title>Automating configuration compliance verification for Cisco Switches</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/22/automating-configuration-compliance-verification-for-cisco-switches/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/22/automating-configuration-compliance-verification-for-cisco-switches/</guid><description>This article stems from a colleague&amp;rsquo;s request to automate the configuration compliance checks for hundreds of switches spread across the globe.
Introduction Ensuring configuration compliance is essential for:
Verifying that devices meet expected configurations.</description></item><item><title>Cisco automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/22/cisco-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/22/cisco-automation-series/</guid><description>Welcome to our series on Cisco Automation Solutions! In this series, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore how Cisco&amp;rsquo;s powerful tools and technologies, like Catalys
Welcome to our series on Cisco Automation Solutions! In this series, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore how Cisco&amp;rsquo;s powerful tools and technologies, like Catalyst Center, APIs, and SDKs, can help automate network management, optimize configurations, and improve device monitoring.</description></item><item><title>Ansible Workbook for DevNetOps slides</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/15/ansible-workbook-for-devnetops-slides/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/15/ansible-workbook-for-devnetops-slides/</guid><description>Explore the comprehensive slides from our Ansible Workbook for DevNetOps course, designed to enhance your understanding of automation and orchestration. These slides cover key concepts, practical applications, and hands-on exercises that will help you master Ansible.</description></item><item><title>Ansible orchestrators and integration tools</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/13/ansible-orchestrators-and-integration-tools/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/13/ansible-orchestrators-and-integration-tools/</guid><description>In this course, we used Ansible manually. To take the next step, we need an orchestrator that can help organize playbooks, manage execution, and generate reports.
There are several solutions available, and in this post, we will describe the most popular ones.</description></item><item><title>Cisco automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/01/cisco-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/01/cisco-automation-series/</guid><description>Welcome to our series on Cisco Automation Solutions! In this series, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore how Cisco&amp;rsquo;s powerful tools and technologies, like Catalyst Center, APIs, and SDKs, can help automate network management, optimize configurations, and improve device monitoring.</description></item><item><title>Enhancing Ansible output</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/01/enhancing-ansible-output/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2025/01/01/enhancing-ansible-output/</guid><description>By default, the output of Ansible shows us the tasks executed, for each device, with a brief summary at the end of what has been done. The color determines the outcome of the task: green if no changes were made, yellow if the configuration was modified, red in case of an error, and blue if the task was skipped.</description></item><item><title>Password Management with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/25/password-management-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/25/password-management-with-ansible/</guid><description>Password management is one of the topics that should be analyzed during the design phase, i.e., before starting to write code. However, from a learning perspective, I prefer to postpone the topic in order to have some basic knowledge.</description></item><item><title>Key takeaways from the Ansible course</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/18/key-takeaways-from-the-ansible-course/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/18/key-takeaways-from-the-ansible-course/</guid><description>We have seen that Ansible is an excellent tool for enhancing operations by automating tasks and orchestrating processes. Ansible&amp;rsquo;s procedural structure makes it easy to transform manual tasks into automated ones: if we can describe a task, we can build a playbook to implement it.</description></item><item><title>Comprehensive Ansible Lab</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/11/comprehensive-ansible-lab/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/11/comprehensive-ansible-lab/</guid><description>In the final exercise, we&amp;rsquo;ll see how to put together what we&amp;rsquo;ve learned to configure and manage a legacy fabric (based on STP).
So let&amp;rsquo;s open the Cisco Legacy Core-Access topology lab, start all the devices, and make sure they&amp;rsquo;re reachable.</description></item><item><title>Review of SNMP Fundamentals</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/04/review-of-snmp-fundamentals/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/04/review-of-snmp-fundamentals/</guid><description>SNMP is a protocol developed to manage network devices. Initially, it was designed to configure devices, monitor them, and receive push alerts. SNMP was first conceived in 1988 and has evolved over time.</description></item><item><title>Key steps for Real-World success</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/27/key-steps-for-real-world-success/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/27/key-steps-for-real-world-success/</guid><description>Before launching any automation project, even before opening our editor, we need to define the essential steps for project success. Equally important is understanding the most common reasons automation projects can fail.</description></item><item><title>Running Ansible playbooks through a Bastion host</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/20/running-ansible-playbooks-through-a-bastion-host/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/20/running-ansible-playbooks-through-a-bastion-host/</guid><description>In many environments, there exists a particularly secure host that must handle all management operations performed by operators on production environments. This host is usually subject to audits and continuous verification.</description></item><item><title>Boosting Ansible performance</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/13/boosting-ansible-performance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/13/boosting-ansible-performance/</guid><description>While Ansible is an ideal choice in terms of accessibility, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly not the best choice for those seeking performance.
Let&amp;rsquo;s look at some specific configurations that allow us to improve performance in a simple way.</description></item><item><title>Ansible parsers and filters</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/06/ansible-parsers-and-filters/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/11/06/ansible-parsers-and-filters/</guid><description>The method we are using with Ansible is called &amp;ldquo;screen-scraper&amp;rdquo;, meaning the interaction with the device is not done through APIs but via CLI, emulating human activity. While this approach might be straightforward when typing commands, reading the outputs can be particularly challenging.</description></item><item><title>Preparing VyOS image for UNetLab v3</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/30/preparing-vyos-image-for-unetlab-v3/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/30/preparing-vyos-image-for-unetlab-v3/</guid><description>As our first image, we choose to use VyOS, which is publicly available on GitHub . We will work from a single host, and later we can distribute our image. Let&amp;rsquo;s download the image to the host:</description></item><item><title>UNetLab v3 architecture</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/23/unetlab-v3-architecture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/23/unetlab-v3-architecture/</guid><description>UNetLab&amp;rsquo;s architecture involves several components that need to interact with each other and report task progress to the user. We can identify the following components:
The web interface allows users to interact with UNetLab, manage users, and labs.</description></item><item><title>Using Ansible handlers for optimized task execution</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/16/using-ansible-handlers-for-optimized-task-execution/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/16/using-ansible-handlers-for-optimized-task-execution/</guid><description>Handlers allow you to associate actions with tasks that make changes to devices. The key feature of handlers is that they are executed once, right before the end of the playbook.</description></item><item><title>Handling errors in Ansible playbooks</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/09/handling-errors-in-ansible-playbooks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/09/handling-errors-in-ansible-playbooks/</guid><description>When developing playbooks, it&amp;rsquo;s often necessary to modify Ansible&amp;rsquo;s default behavior in case of errors.
Here are three common scenarios:
When a task should only run in a specific mode When a task should never report changes When a task should fail under certain conditions Additionally, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore three scenarios that are useful to know but rarely encountered in practice.</description></item><item><title>Installing EVE-NG 6</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/05/installing-eve-ng-6/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/05/installing-eve-ng-6/</guid><description>EVE-NG is installed from packages downloaded from the official repository via APT. All the following commands should be executed by the root user via SSH.
First, we add the official repository and the GPG key to verify the packages:</description></item><item><title>Strategies for troubleshooting Ansible errors</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/02/strategies-for-troubleshooting-ansible-errors/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/02/strategies-for-troubleshooting-ansible-errors/</guid><description>One of the biggest challenges when using Ansible, especially at the beginning, is troubleshooting. You often run into errors that are unclear, poorly described, or misleading.
Let&amp;rsquo;s look at some strategies to help resolve otherwise incomprehensible errors.</description></item><item><title>Preparing a Proxmox cluster for UNetLab v3</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/30/preparing-a-proxmox-cluster-for-unetlab-v3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/30/preparing-a-proxmox-cluster-for-unetlab-v3/</guid><description>UNetLab requires a cluster with one or more correctly configured PVE hosts. This page contains all the commands needed to configure a PVE host.
Install the custom kernel for UNetLab To enable L1 links, UNetLab needs a kernel with a specific patch.</description></item><item><title>Contributing to NTC Templates with Git and GitHub</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/25/contributing-to-ntc-templates-with-git-and-github/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/25/contributing-to-ntc-templates-with-git-and-github/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s finally see how to contribute to an open-source project. We&amp;rsquo;ll use the NTC-Templates project as a practical example, for which I have already developed 46 patches .
Let&amp;rsquo;s assume we&amp;rsquo;ve already made the necessary changes, and now we want to propose them for official inclusion in the NTC Templates repository.</description></item><item><title>Advanced Git commands</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/19/advanced-git-commands/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/19/advanced-git-commands/</guid><description>In the last two posts, we covered most of the essential Git features. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s dive into some additional functionalities that might come in handy.
.gitignore The .gitignore file is used to specify which files or directories should never be included in your Git repository.</description></item><item><title>Ansible statements</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/16/ansible-statements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/16/ansible-statements/</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve got some experience with programming languages, you might find Ansible&amp;rsquo;s constructs a bit clunky. But no worries, let&amp;rsquo;s break them down with some practical examples to make things clearer.</description></item><item><title>Lab modeling for UNetLab v3</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/13/lab-modeling-for-unetlab-v3/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/13/lab-modeling-for-unetlab-v3/</guid><description>We&amp;rsquo;ve run a series of field tests to check if the idea we&amp;rsquo;re working on is feasible and functional. The results are positive, the APIs support most of the key features (but not all).</description></item><item><title>Collaborating with Git by working with remote repositories and forks</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/10/collaborating-with-git-by-working-with-remote-repositories-and-forks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/10/collaborating-with-git-by-working-with-remote-repositories-and-forks/</guid><description>In the previous post, we covered the basics of using Git locally. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s dive into real-world scenarios and learn how to collaborate using Git with remote repositories.
When working with remote repositories, we gain access to some new functionalities:</description></item><item><title>Git fundamentals for developers and IT professionals</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/06/git-fundamentals-for-developers-and-it-professionals/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/06/git-fundamentals-for-developers-and-it-professionals/</guid><description>Git is a distributed version control software created by Linus Torvalds to manage the Linux kernel source code . Personally, I use Git, along with GitHub , to manage:
The source code for the software I develop ; The source code and compiled files for my website ; The source code for the books I&amp;rsquo;ve written ; My notes, written with Obsidian .</description></item><item><title>Defining and using variables in Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/01/defining-and-using-variables-in-ansible/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/01/defining-and-using-variables-in-ansible/</guid><description>Variables in Ansible can be defined in various ways, offering flexibility in managing configuration and customizing playbooks.
Defining Variables in the Playbook: one simple and direct way to define variables is to include them directly in the playbook:</description></item><item><title>Choose your learning path: unlock the power of automation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/29/choose-your-learning-path-unlock-the-power-of-automation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/29/choose-your-learning-path-unlock-the-power-of-automation/</guid><description>Embark on a journey to elevate your network engineering skills by choosing the right path in network automation. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re looking to automate firewall management with Palo Alto Networks, streamline configurations with Ansible, or delve into advanced network emulation with UNetLab, this learning path has you covered.</description></item><item><title>OAuth Client Credentials flow with Patreon</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/26/oauth-client-credentials-flow-with-patreon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/26/oauth-client-credentials-flow-with-patreon/</guid><description>In the previous post, we covered how to implement the Authorization Code flow (3-legged) using the OAuth 2.0 Framework. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s explore a practical example of the Client Credentials flow (2-legged).</description></item><item><title>OAuth Authorization Code flow with Patreon</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/24/oauth-authorization-code-flow-with-patreon/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/24/oauth-authorization-code-flow-with-patreon/</guid><description>In our previous post, we introduced the OAuth 2.0 Framework. Now, let&amp;rsquo;s dive into a practical example using the Authorization Code flow (3-legged).
The term &amp;ldquo;authorization code&amp;rdquo; refers to the fact that, in the process, we exchange a temporary token (authorization code) for an access token, which will grant us access to protected resources.</description></item><item><title>Diving into OAuth 2.0</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/21/diving-into-oauth-2.0/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/21/diving-into-oauth-2.0/</guid><description>In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll delve into some key concepts of the OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework . Understanding OAuth 2.0 is crucial for working with APIs that are protected by this mechanism.</description></item><item><title>Configuring Incident Classification in Cortex XSOAR</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/19/configuring-incident-classification-in-cortex-xsoar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/19/configuring-incident-classification-in-cortex-xsoar/</guid><description>In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll set up the classification feature, which allows us to transform events into specific incident types. This guide expands on the content covered in the videos XSOAR Engineer Training - Part 2: Incident Types &amp;amp; Fields and XSOAR Engineer Training - Part 3: Classification and Mapping .</description></item><item><title>Ansible Playbooks and variables</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/15/ansible-playbooks-and-variables/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/15/ansible-playbooks-and-variables/</guid><description>A playbook is a YAML file that sequentially outlines the operations to be performed on devices or groups of devices. Each playbook is composed of one or more plays, which can include pre_tasks, tasks, and post_tasks.</description></item><item><title>Palo Alto Networks automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/13/palo-alto-networks-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/13/palo-alto-networks-automation-series/</guid><description>This series of Patreon posts dives deep into the automation of Palo Alto Networks devices and software, offering you a comprehensive guide to streamlining and optimizing your security operations. Throughout the series, we explore how to automate various components, including firewalls, Cortex XDR, and Cortex XSOAR, to enhance your network security and incident response capabilities.</description></item><item><title>Introducing Cortex XSOAR</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/12/introducing-cortex-xsoar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/12/introducing-cortex-xsoar/</guid><description>Cortex XSOAR is a comprehensive orchestration and automation system that unifies all the components of your security infrastructure. It seamlessly integrates with your third-party security and incident management vendors, allowing you to trigger events that automatically become incidents within Cortex XSOAR.</description></item><item><title>Setting Up Your Cortex XSOAR Lab Environment</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/12/setting-up-your-cortex-xsoar-lab-environment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/12/setting-up-your-cortex-xsoar-lab-environment/</guid><description>In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll guide you through setting up a lab environment for experimenting with Palo Alto Networks&amp;rsquo; Cortex XSOAR. This tutorial aligns with the content from the video XSOAR Engineer Training - Part 2: Incident Types &amp;amp; Fields .</description></item><item><title>Ansible configuration</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/05/ansible-configuration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/05/ansible-configuration/</guid><description>Ansible typically works out-of-the-box without requiring additional configuration. However, advanced usage might necessitate some customization. Ansible can be configured through files or variables.
For example, the DEFAULT_HOST_LIST parameter defines the inventory file.</description></item><item><title>Testing stretched networks with Proxmox</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/04/testing-stretched-networks-with-proxmox/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/04/testing-stretched-networks-with-proxmox/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s explore how Proxmox&amp;rsquo;s SDN functionality works. We&amp;rsquo;ll use the SDN structure to implement extended L2 networks, enabling us to run labs across multiple hosts.
Create an SDN Zone First, create a zone:</description></item><item><title>Ansible ad hoc commands</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/03/ansible-ad-hoc-commands/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/03/ansible-ad-hoc-commands/</guid><description>Ansible provides a way to execute single commands without the need to build playbooks. This mode is called ad hoc and can be useful for executing one-time commands in very specific scenarios.</description></item><item><title>Ansible inventory</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/02/ansible-inventory/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/02/ansible-inventory/</guid><description>The inventory is the source of truth containing the information that Ansible will use to connect to devices. The inventory also allows defining variables at the host or group level. Particularly, variables can be used, in advanced scenarios, to define all infrastructure parameters, such as interfaces, IP addresses, router ID, etc.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Ansible Automation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/01/introduction-to-ansible-automation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/08/01/introduction-to-ansible-automation/</guid><description>Ansible is often described as an agentless automation framework. However, it relies on Python, which must be installed along with certain modules on the hosts where playbooks are executed. In this sense, Python acts as the necessary &amp;ldquo;agent&amp;rdquo; on the remote system.</description></item><item><title>Preparing your Ansible environment</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/31/preparing-your-ansible-environment/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/31/preparing-your-ansible-environment/</guid><description>Ansible , based on Python , can be easily installed using the package manager PIP . The functionalities of Ansible available obviously depend on its version, which is closely tied to the version of Python in use.</description></item><item><title>Fundamentals of network automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/29/fundamentals-of-network-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/29/fundamentals-of-network-automation-series/</guid><description>In this series, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the core principles of network automation, essential tools, and practical techniques to streamline your network operations. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re new to the field or looking to sharpen your skills, our posts will provide the foundational knowledge you need to succeed.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to network automation with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/28/introduction-to-network-automation-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/28/introduction-to-network-automation-with-ansible/</guid><description>Welcome to our series focused on Network Automation with Ansible! This series is designed to help you streamline operations, standardize workflows, and manage multiple devices in significantly less time. Network automation is no longer just the domain of network engineers; it is now expanding to include Governance, Risk, and Compliance (GRC) teams.</description></item><item><title>Ansible automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/ansible-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/ansible-automation-series/</guid><description>Welcome to our series focused on Ansible Automation! In this comprehensive series, we&amp;rsquo;ll delve into Ansible, an incredibly powerful tool designed to automate a wide range of IT tasks and streamline the management of complex deployments.</description></item><item><title>Automating EVE-NG installation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/automating-eve-ng-installation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/automating-eve-ng-installation/</guid><description>Installing an EVE-NG server is a task I encounter every time I need to prepare a new course. For this reason, I have created an Ansible playbook that, starting from an Ubuntu Linux Server 22.</description></item><item><title>Customizing EVE-NG</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/customizing-eve-ng/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/customizing-eve-ng/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s delve into the most important part: customizing EVE-NG for DevNetOps. In particular, we will proceed to:
Configure an internal network dedicated to device management. Import the labs from the GitHub repository dedicated to DevNetOps courses.</description></item><item><title>Installing EVE-NG 5</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/installing-eve-ng-5/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/installing-eve-ng-5/</guid><description>EVE-NG is installed from packages downloaded from the official repository via APT. All the following commands should be executed by the root user via SSH.
First, we add the official repository and the GPG key to verify the packages:</description></item><item><title>Installing Ubuntu Linux</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/installing-ubuntu-linux/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/installing-ubuntu-linux/</guid><description>Now let&amp;rsquo;s see how to install Ubuntu Linux Server 20.04 LTS so that it can host EVE-NG.
Virtual Environment In a virtual environment, typically VMware vSphere, I suggest creating a virtual machine with the following specifications:</description></item><item><title>Introduction to EVE-NG platform</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/introduction-to-eve-ng-platform/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/introduction-to-eve-ng-platform/</guid><description>Developing automations that interact with network devices requires having a development environment to test, learn, and experiment with frameworks, integrations, and automations. Virtualization over the years has allowed anyone to have realistic copies of network devices at their disposal.</description></item><item><title>Prerequisites for EVE-NG</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/prerequisites-for-eve-ng/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/27/prerequisites-for-eve-ng/</guid><description>To set up an EVE-NG environment, you&amp;rsquo;ll need some prerequisites in terms of knowledge, hardware, and software.
Skills Generally, diving into the world of network automation requires a solid understanding of Linux system usage and management.</description></item><item><title>Creating templates for Proxmox</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/26/creating-templates-for-proxmox/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/26/creating-templates-for-proxmox/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s prepare templates to generate nodes for our labs. We&amp;rsquo;ll start with VyOS , an open-source router and firewall. VyOS is available as a rolling release and can be downloaded from GitHub in ISO format.</description></item><item><title>Simulating an L1 link in Proxmox</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/26/simulating-an-l1-link-in-proxmox/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/26/simulating-an-l1-link-in-proxmox/</guid><description>We now have all the elements needed to simulate an L1 link. Let&amp;rsquo;s create a simple lab with two interconnected VyOS nodes.
1. Create an L1 network bridge First, create a network bridge that will simulate the L1 link.</description></item><item><title>Patching the Proxmox kernel</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/25/patching-the-proxmox-kernel/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/25/patching-the-proxmox-kernel/</guid><description>Proxmox offers various constructs for building virtual networks. We&amp;rsquo;ll focus on using bridges to emulate physical links, as we did in UNetLab v1.
Linux bridges handle frames differently:
Broadcast frames are forwarded to all ports.</description></item><item><title>Proxmox: optimizing virtualization</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/24/proxmox-optimizing-virtualization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/24/proxmox-optimizing-virtualization/</guid><description>During the development of the first version of UNetLab, I dedicated significant time to creating a flexible QEMU/KVM orchestrator. At that time, virtualization-ready images were rare. Choosing a specific QEMU version or parameter could determine the success or failure of virtualizing a particular device.</description></item><item><title>UNetLab v3: whishing list</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/23/unetlab-v3-whishing-list/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/23/unetlab-v3-whishing-list/</guid><description>The idea behind UNetLab v2 was partly good, but some choices complicated the implementation and negatively impacted system performance. Specifically, managing UNetLab&amp;rsquo;s network in user space would have caused serious problems, even though it would have made horizontal scalability easier.</description></item><item><title>iou-web: the beginning</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/22/iou-web-the-beginning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/22/iou-web-the-beginning/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with network simulators since around 2011 when I decided to pursue my CCIE R&amp;amp;S certification. Around that time, another pivotal event set me on the path of development: Cisco released a binary called IOL (IOS on Linux), which essentially simulated a Cisco IOS router.</description></item><item><title>UNetLab v2: addressing limitations</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/22/unetlab-v2-addressing-limitations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/22/unetlab-v2-addressing-limitations/</guid><description>In recent years, my focus has shifted towards network automation. I still need a unified network emulator platform, but the prerequisites have evolved. Before diving into the new requirements, let&amp;rsquo;s highlight the limitations of UNetLab:</description></item><item><title>UNetLab: the evolution of iou-web</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/22/unetlab-the-evolution-of-iou-web/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/22/unetlab-the-evolution-of-iou-web/</guid><description>In 2013, I realized that iou-web was too limited. I needed a &amp;ldquo;unified&amp;rdquo; approach to emulate a network, including firewalls, load balancers, and more. Additionally, multicasting using IOL was problematic. I had several new prerequisites:</description></item><item><title>Network simulators are a must</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/20/network-simulators-are-a-must/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/20/network-simulators-are-a-must/</guid><description>For anyone working in IT, theory alone isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. Practical experience is crucial to fully grasp concepts and develop the skills needed to design, configure, and manage complex environments. In the early 2000s, network administrators often bought second-hand hardware to build labs for studying and experimenting with configurations before deploying them in production.</description></item><item><title>UNetLab v3 development series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/20/unetlab-v3-development-series/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/20/unetlab-v3-development-series/</guid><description>Join me as I embark on an exciting journey to develop UNetLab v3! On this Patreon series, you&amp;rsquo;ll get an exclusive behind-the-scenes look at the evolution of UNetLab, from initial concepts to advanced configurations.</description></item><item><title>Key insights from developing Nautobot and Ansible integrations</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/12/key-insights-from-developing-nautobot-and-ansible-integrations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/12/key-insights-from-developing-nautobot-and-ansible-integrations/</guid><description>Beyond the topics discussed in previous posts, my work on this project focused on four key areas:
The data structure of Nautobot Nautobot&amp;rsquo;s REST API Integrating Ansible with Nautobot Running Ansible playbooks from Nautobot Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the challenges encountered and the solutions omitted from previous posts.</description></item><item><title>Orchestrating Ansible playbooks for Nautobot integration</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/12/orchestrating-ansible-playbooks-for-nautobot-integration/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/12/orchestrating-ansible-playbooks-for-nautobot-integration/</guid><description>Currently, it is not possible to execute Ansible playbooks directly from Nautobot. There are some proposals , but nothing concrete has been implemented yet.
The only option is to use an external orchestrator to run the playbook regularly or upon operator request.</description></item><item><title>The Ansible role breakdown</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/12/the-ansible-role-breakdown/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/12/the-ansible-role-breakdown/</guid><description>Now, we need to translate the interface roles defined in Nautobot into specific configurations for the switches. To achieve this, we will create an Ansible role that utilizes the inventory described in the previous post to configure the interfaces of each device.</description></item><item><title>Integrating Ansible with Nautobot</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/11/integrating-ansible-with-nautobot/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/11/integrating-ansible-with-nautobot/</guid><description>Integrating Ansible with Nautobot involves two main aspects:
Reading information from Nautobot using Ansible. Running Ansible playbooks to update device configurations. Let&amp;rsquo;s focus on the first point: to make Nautobot&amp;rsquo;s information available in Ansible, we need to use a dynamic inventory .</description></item><item><title>Nautobot automation series</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/11/nautobot-automation-series/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/11/nautobot-automation-series/</guid><description>Welcome to our Patreon-exclusive series on Nautobot Automations! If you&amp;rsquo;re an IT professional, network engineer, or automation enthusiast, this is your gateway to mastering network automation using Nautobot.
Nautobot is an open-source Network Source of Truth and Network Automation Platform.</description></item><item><title>Choosing the foundation for our SSOT</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/choosing-the-foundation-for-our-ssot/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/choosing-the-foundation-for-our-ssot/</guid><description>The first topic we need to address is selecting the software that will serve as the foundation for our SSOT (Single Source of Truth). Our ultimate goal is to create a data structure that consolidates all the critical information about our infrastructure, such as:</description></item><item><title>Installing Nautobot in your lab environment</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/installing-nautobot-in-your-lab-environment/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/installing-nautobot-in-your-lab-environment/</guid><description>In this guide, we&amp;rsquo;ll walk through installing Nautobot in a lab environment. For production installation, please refer to the official documentation . Nautobot requires Python versions between 3.8 and 3.11. First, ensure you have the correct Python version:</description></item><item><title>Leveraging Nautobot as a SSOT</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/leveraging-nautobot-as-a-ssot/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/leveraging-nautobot-as-a-ssot/</guid><description>Every company should move away from using Excel sheets as databases for managing infrastructure and switch to a structured system as the foundation for operational workflows.
The goal is to have a single repository that contains all the infrastructure data, including:</description></item><item><title>Populating our SSOT with Automation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/populating-our-ssot-with-automation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/07/10/populating-our-ssot-with-automation/</guid><description>Now, we need to populate our Single Source of Truth (SSOT). Manually adding interfaces for each device is impractical. Hence, automating this process by reading device configurations and creating corresponding SSOT objects is essential.</description></item><item><title>Palo Alto Firewall as Code</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/06/22/palo-alto-firewall-as-code/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/06/22/palo-alto-firewall-as-code/</guid><description>It has been about 6 years since the Automate IT² event organized by me and Gabriele Gerbino. During the event, Xavier Homes presented a case that fascinated me. Today we might call it: Firewall as Code.</description></item><item><title>The cost of complexity: Ansible AWX</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/05/05/the-cost-of-complexity-ansible-awx/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/05/05/the-cost-of-complexity-ansible-awx/</guid><description>For several years now, Ansible AWX has been on my ToDo list. I have always postponed dealing with it due to its complexity, but today I find myself having to tackle it.</description></item><item><title>Ansible Workbook</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/27/ansible-workbook/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/27/ansible-workbook/</guid><description>Network automation arises as a necessity to reduce and enhance operability, standardize working methods, and operate on multiple devices in significantly reduced times. The number of individuals interested in this approach is steadily expanding: starting from network engineer teams, automation is now attracting GRC (Governance Risk and Compliance) teams.</description></item><item><title>EVE-NG Workbook (Amazon Kindle)</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/25/eve-ng-workbook-amazon-kindle/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/25/eve-ng-workbook-amazon-kindle/</guid><description>Developing automations that interact with network devices requires having a development environment to test, learn, and experiment with frameworks, integrations, and automations. Virtualization over the years has allowed anyone to have realistic copies of network devices at their disposal.</description></item><item><title>Configuring NTP on Cisco IOS with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/11/04/configuring-ntp-on-cisco-ios-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/11/04/configuring-ntp-on-cisco-ios-with-ansible/</guid><description>This article serves as an example to explore different strategies for configuring a feature on network devices using Ansible. Specifically, we will focus on configuring NTP on Cisco IOS devices, although the discussions here can be generalized.</description></item><item><title>Automatic Cisco XR provisioning with ZTP</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/10/18/automatic-cisco-xr-provisioning-with-ztp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/10/18/automatic-cisco-xr-provisioning-with-ztp/</guid><description>This article explores how to optimize the provisioning of a hundred Cisco XR devices so that they are configured with minimal human intervention. Depending on the context, the devices might be shipped directly from the factory and configured automatically on-site, or more likely, they could be automatically configured in a lab environment, verified, and then shipped for installation.</description></item><item><title>Ansible Navigator</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/10/06/ansible-navigator/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/10/06/ansible-navigator/</guid><description>Ansible Navigator is a container-based textual interface designed to manage various components of Ansible. In essence, it serves as a wrapper, providing a unified interface to the Ansible ecosystem. Initially, the use of Ansible Navigator does not require container usage; thus, we will use the --ee=false parameter.</description></item><item><title>Debug all variables with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/10/06/debug-all-variables-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/10/06/debug-all-variables-with-ansible/</guid><description>When working with Ansible, one of the &amp;ldquo;recipes&amp;rdquo; that I always keep handy is related to debugging variables. I find it particularly useful to have a comprehensive view of the variables associated with a host, defined at the &amp;ldquo;facts&amp;rdquo;, environment, group, and host levels.</description></item><item><title>Ansible inventory</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/30/ansible-inventory/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/30/ansible-inventory/</guid><description>In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the two methods for defining an inventory usable by Ansible. The inventory serves as the source of truth containing the information that Ansible will use to connect to devices.</description></item><item><title>Set up the first laboratory on EVE-NG</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/30/set-up-the-first-laboratory-on-eve-ng/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/30/set-up-the-first-laboratory-on-eve-ng/</guid><description>In the realm of automation, each laboratory we will create requires a feature as basic as it is essential: the IP addresses of the devices must be accessible from the automation system.</description></item><item><title>Loops and nested loops with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/29/loops-and-nested-loops-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/29/loops-and-nested-loops-with-ansible/</guid><description>In my opinion, one of the less understandable constructs in Ansible concerns loop management. If we then talk about nested loops, the situation becomes even more complex. In this short post, we&amp;rsquo;ll see the recipes for:</description></item><item><title>Task and process automation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/27/task-and-process-automation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/27/task-and-process-automation/</guid><description>I have been involved in automation since around 2004, when I was managing nearly 200 nodes on the AlphaServer. Specifically, I was responsible for the hardware aspect. It may seem straightforward, but it&amp;rsquo;s important to consider that there was a mini operating system running under Unix that checked the connected components, detecting both critical and non-critical errors.</description></item><item><title>One-time commands on Cisco IOS with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/25/one-time-commands-on-cisco-ios-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/25/one-time-commands-on-cisco-ios-with-ansible/</guid><description>In this article, we present an initial example of executing mass commands using Ansible on Cisco IOS devices. We will utilize the pre-configured &amp;ldquo;Cisco Legacy Core-Access topology&amp;rdquo; lab available in the repository DevNetOps course material:</description></item><item><title>Installing Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/24/installing-ansible/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/24/installing-ansible/</guid><description>Ansible is distributed as a Python module installable via PIP. The installation process is straightforward but warrants some considerations.
Typically, the automation host, the system from which all automation scripts originate, is one of the most critical systems within an infrastructure.</description></item><item><title>Installing EVE-NG</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/21/installing-eve-ng/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/09/21/installing-eve-ng/</guid><description>The first step to work in the IT field today is to set up a laboratory. EVE-NG (formerly UNetLab) can be used for network, network security, and automation labs.
EVE-NG is based on Ubuntu Linux 20.</description></item><item><title>Speed up DC/ISP operation with automation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/08/12/speed-up-dc/isp-operation-with-automation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2023/08/12/speed-up-dc/isp-operation-with-automation/</guid><description>Operating on a data center (DC) or backbone Internet Service Provider (ISP) typically involves a significant amount of human effort, resulting in operational costs that are often overlooked. However, these costs can be optimized by harnessing the power of automation to handle simple and repetitive tasks efficiently.</description></item><item><title>Improving IaC with Spacelift</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/10/31/improving-iac-with-spacelift/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/10/31/improving-iac-with-spacelift/</guid><description>This is the third part of my IaC overview based on a personal experiment: building Cyber range using the IaC paradigm. Here is the first and second parts.
A few weeks ago I met Spacelift and I had the chance to test their product.</description></item><item><title>Ansible with bastion host</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/10/30/ansible-with-bastion-host/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/10/30/ansible-with-bastion-host/</guid><description>This is the second part of my IaC overview based on a personal experiment: building Cyber range using the IaC paradigm. Here are the first and third parts.
In a pure design perspective, the client-to-site VPN approach is still the best.</description></item><item><title>Infrastructure as code for Cyber Ranges</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/10/29/infrastructure-as-code-for-cyber-ranges/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/10/29/infrastructure-as-code-for-cyber-ranges/</guid><description>This is the first part of my IaC overview based on a personal experiment: building Cyber range using the IaC paradigm. Here are the second and third parts.
During my Twitch session, I&amp;rsquo;m used to offering a practical lab to attendees.</description></item><item><title>NetDoc: automated network discovery and documentation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/08/28/netdoc-automated-network-discovery-and-documentation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/08/28/netdoc-automated-network-discovery-and-documentation/</guid><description>Years ago I worked on a data center migration project. I was in charge to review network documentation, and automating the configuration, testing, and migration phases. There is no chance to review dozens of switches manually, so I wrote some Python scripts to get neighborship and configuration from switches, drawing Visio diagrams.</description></item><item><title>Automating Google searches</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/07/17/automating-google-searches/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/07/17/automating-google-searches/</guid><description>I usually don&amp;rsquo;t write about OSINT techniques, I think that before approaching OSINT we should speak about ethics and respect. By the way, some OSINT automation techniques are harmless: if you don&amp;rsquo;t know what you have to search for, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to get anything regardless you are automating or not.</description></item><item><title>Automatic CIS controls check with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/07/15/automatic-cis-controls-check-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/07/15/automatic-cis-controls-check-with-ansible/</guid><description>Security assessments are part of my daily job, and automation is part of my mindset. CIS Controls provides a set of standard controls that should be checked on&amp;hellip; anything. To be specific CIS also provides a benchmark (a sort of step-by-step guide) for many environments.</description></item><item><title>Automating Palo Alto Networks firewalls</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/02/02/automating-palo-alto-networks-firewalls/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/02/02/automating-palo-alto-networks-firewalls/</guid><description>I spent a few Twitch sessions speaking about the automation of Palo Alto Networks firewalls. We used different approaches than the one used with Cisco devices. Initially, we developed a few simple Ansible playbooks.</description></item><item><title>Automating Cisco devices with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/01/13/automating-cisco-devices-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/01/13/automating-cisco-devices-with-ansible/</guid><description>I spent a few Twitch sessions speaking about the automation of Cisco devices with Ansible. I don&amp;rsquo;t think Ansible is the best tool and the best way to automate tasks on Cisco devices, but a well-designed and well-documented Ansible playbook can be maintained by non NetDevOps guys too.</description></item><item><title>Contributing to NTC-Templates</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/12/30/contributing-to-ntc-templates/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/12/30/contributing-to-ntc-templates/</guid><description>A few weeks ago a customer asked me to patch NTC Templates because it has a very old HP Procurve switch. I&amp;rsquo;m used to patching NTC Templates, it&amp;rsquo;s an important tool for my automation tasks.</description></item><item><title>Clean a Docker host</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/08/11/clean-a-docker-host/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/08/11/clean-a-docker-host/</guid><description>The following scripts allow cleaning a Docker host, and stopping and deleting containers and images.
Stop all containers:
#!/bin/bash CONTAINERS=$(docker ps -a | tail -n+2 | cut -d&amp;#34; &amp;#34; -f1) if [ &amp;#34;$CONTAINERS&amp;#34; == &amp;#34;&amp;#34; ]; then exit fi docker stop $CONTAINERS Stop and delete all containers:</description></item><item><title>Override a Docker container entry point</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/08/10/override-a-docker-container-entry-point/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/08/10/override-a-docker-container-entry-point/</guid><description>To debug a container or to access it, sometimes I need to override the entry point for a specific image:
docker run -it --entrypoint /bin/sh [docker_image]</description></item><item><title>Reinitialize a Git repository</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/07/reinitialize-a-git-repository/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/07/reinitialize-a-git-repository/</guid><description>Sometimes we realize we committed something that should remain confidential. Or maybe we are ready to publish our open source project and we don&amp;rsquo;t want to publish the entire history too.</description></item><item><title>Ansible with a bastion host (SSH Proxy)</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2020/08/14/ansible-with-a-bastion-host-ssh-proxy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2020/08/14/ansible-with-a-bastion-host-ssh-proxy/</guid><description>On some Ansible designs, I need to use a bastion host to log in to remote servers. We can configure it in the following way:
on ansible.cfg file:
[defaults] timeout = 25 gathering = smart # utile ma non essenziale [ssh_connection] #ssh_args = -o ControlMaster=auto -o ControlPersist=600s ssh_args = -o ControlMaster=auto -o ControlPersist=600s -o UserKnownHostsFile=/dev/null -o StrictHostKeyChecking=nocontrol_path = %(directory)s/%%h-%%r pipelining = True on the inventory file:</description></item><item><title>APT proxy with APT-Cacher NG</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2020/08/13/apt-proxy-with-apt-cacher-ng/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2020/08/13/apt-proxy-with-apt-cacher-ng/</guid><description>On large Linux Debian installations, I usually configure an APT proxy to optimize upgrades. I&amp;rsquo;m used to configuring APT-Cached NG in the following way:
on /etc/apt-cacher-ng/acng.conf file:
CacheDir: /proxydata/cache/apt-cacher-ng LogDir: /var/log/apt-cacher-ng SupportDir: /usr/lib/apt-cacher-ng Port:3142 Remap-debrep: file:deb_mirror*.</description></item><item><title>A summary of automation tools for Cisco (and non Cisco) devices</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2018/12/17/a-summary-of-automation-tools-for-cisco-and-non-cisco-devices/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2018/12/17/a-summary-of-automation-tools-for-cisco-and-non-cisco-devices/</guid><description>A few months ago I prepared a short introduction to automation for a small group of colleagues. Now I would like to summarize in a few posts what I explained to them just to share an overview.</description></item><item><title>Is SDN just a buzzword? (part 2)</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2018/09/11/is-sdn-just-a-buzzword-part-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2018/09/11/is-sdn-just-a-buzzword-part-2/</guid><description>A question comes up to my mind few weeks ago: can enterprises operate on networks like they are doing with software today? In other words: can enterprise start to automate things without buying additional solutions?</description></item><item><title>Automatic network discovery and documentation</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2017/03/28/automatic-network-discovery-and-documentation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2017/03/28/automatic-network-discovery-and-documentation/</guid><description>NetBrain is a famous software that allows network discovery (and management). Let&amp;rsquo;s focus now on network discovery and documentation: we want to automatically discover network devices, and how they&amp;rsquo;re connected, and store everything into a version control repository (GIT/CVS).</description></item><item><title>Managing NTP on Cisco IOS with Ansible</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2017/02/17/managing-ntp-on-cisco-ios-with-ansible/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2017/02/17/managing-ntp-on-cisco-ios-with-ansible/</guid><description>After installing Ansible (see previous post), it&amp;rsquo;s now time to manage how to send multiple commands (and check) to Cisco IOS devices. This post will explain a playbook (recipe) for clock and NTP configuration.</description></item><item><title>Restart DSL connection on a CRC threshold using EEM</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2014/03/06/restart-dsl-connection-on-a-crc-threshold-using-eem/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2014/03/06/restart-dsl-connection-on-a-crc-threshold-using-eem/</guid><description>My Internet connection is cheap enough and a little bit crappy. Cisco provides Embedded Event Manager (EEM), useful to manage a situation like mine:
event manager applet RESTART_ATM event interface name &amp;#34;ATM0&amp;#34; parameter input_errors_crc entry-val 3000 entry-op gt entry-val-is-increment true exit-comb or exit-val 1 exit-op le exit-val-is-increment true exit-time 5 poll-interval 3600 maxrun 10 action 1.</description></item><item><title>Create email with attachment using BASH</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2013/08/12/create-email-with-attachment-using-bash/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2013/08/12/create-email-with-attachment-using-bash/</guid><description>I replaced most of my Bash script with Python but sometimes I still need Bash. The following script requires uuencode and sends an email with attachments using Bash:
#!/bin/bash PATH=&amp;#34;/usr/local/sbin:/usr/local/bin:/sbin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/usr/bin&amp;#34; EMAIL_OK=&amp;#34;dainese@example.</description></item></channel></rss>