<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ciso on Andrea Dainese</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/categories/ciso/</link><description>Recent content in ciso on Andrea Dainese</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.adainese.it/categories/ciso/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Vulnerability Management</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/02/vulnerability-management/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/12/02/vulnerability-management/</guid><description>A lot has already been said about Vulnerability Management (VM), and I&amp;rsquo;ve personally touched on this topic several times before. Yet, the reality is that managing vulnerabilities remains a significant challenge for most organizations.</description></item><item><title>Assume breach design</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/12/assume-breach-design/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/10/12/assume-breach-design/</guid><description>There is much discussion around Zero Trust Architecture (ZTA), but it seems the concept of Assume Breach Design has yet to be formalized. Or, at least, a Google search does not yield results.</description></item><item><title>ICS/OT/IoT Security: challenges and protection strategies</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/05/ics/ot/iot-security-challenges-and-protection-strategies/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/09/05/ics/ot/iot-security-challenges-and-protection-strategies/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s time to revisit the ICS/OT world, as it has unique characteristics that influence its processes and tools.
First, I would categorize this broad field into the following groups:
Systems localized within a confined area (e.</description></item><item><title>Palo Alto Firewall as Code</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/06/22/palo-alto-firewall-as-code/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/06/22/palo-alto-firewall-as-code/</guid><description>It has been about 6 years since the Automate IT² event organized by me and Gabriele Gerbino. During the event, Xavier Homes presented a case that fascinated me. Today we might call it: Firewall as Code.</description></item><item><title>On the other side of the Firewall</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/06/11/on-the-other-side-of-the-firewall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/06/11/on-the-other-side-of-the-firewall/</guid><description>This book originates from the authors&amp;rsquo; experience in conducting security incident simulations within companies. The scenarios described are always based on real cases, modified to make them unrecognizable while still usable as tabletop exercises.</description></item><item><title>Opt-out from Web Archive</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/29/opt-out-from-web-archive/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/29/opt-out-from-web-archive/</guid><description>Web Archive is an online service (non-profit) that has long been recording various websites by archiving them in a virtually permanent manner so that anyone can analyze the history and changes of a specific website.</description></item><item><title>Cybersecurity: fashion or strategy</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/11/cybersecurity-fashion-or-strategy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2024/04/11/cybersecurity-fashion-or-strategy/</guid><description>I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a suitable title for this post, in which I try to gather various insights that I&amp;rsquo;ve received in the past few days and that I&amp;rsquo;ve planned, sooner or later, to discuss together with Rocco Sicilia.</description></item><item><title>Securing user authentication under IEC 62443 in OT</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/06/15/securing-user-authentication-under-iec-62443-in-ot/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/06/15/securing-user-authentication-under-iec-62443-in-ot/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m discussing the IEC 62443 certification with an organization: that build and sell ICS plants which are risky from a safety perspective. They currently comply with the Machinery Directive (Directive 2006/42/EC of the European Parliament), but they are not considering the Cyber risk.</description></item><item><title>What does it take to secure any SME organization?</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/05/25/what-does-it-take-to-secure-any-sme-organization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/05/25/what-does-it-take-to-secure-any-sme-organization/</guid><description>Managing Cybersecurity is expensive, we all know that. But not managing it is also more expensive. Given my experience, an SME recovers from a critical Cyberattack in 5-10 days, if it can recover (yes I also personally know companies that lost everything because of a Cyberattack).</description></item><item><title>Log management is more than a log collector</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/05/20/log-management-is-more-than-a-log-collector/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/05/20/log-management-is-more-than-a-log-collector/</guid><description>Many companies (hopefully) are collecting logs in a central system. The reason besides that is for compliance and sometimes for root cause analysis. In this post, I want to recap that log management is not just about log collections, and why and how the process should be designed.</description></item><item><title>The value of a Risk Based VA</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/05/18/the-value-of-a-risk-based-va/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/05/18/the-value-of-a-risk-based-va/</guid><description>In this article, I&amp;rsquo;m explaining why we are executing VA, why the traditional approach is dangerous and how we should manage the risk bound to vulnerabilities.
I&amp;rsquo;m also discussing a few false myths about VA.</description></item><item><title>VA scanners for patch management: good or bad?</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/03/29/va-scanners-for-patch-management-good-or-bad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/03/29/va-scanners-for-patch-management-good-or-bad/</guid><description>Nowadays (hopefully) all companies are executing regular vulnerability assessments. They often use different partners/tools each year and they often limit themselves to vulnerability assessments.
VAs are not the end of a security strategy, they are just a small step at the beginning.</description></item><item><title>Approaching OT/ICS Cybersecurity</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/03/28/approaching-ot/ics-cybersecurity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2022/03/28/approaching-ot/ics-cybersecurity/</guid><description>A few days ago, together with Rocco Sicilia and FESTO Academy , I presented a webinar on OT/ICS Cybersecurity approach. We are often spending time increasing Cybersecurity awareness, and that webinar was focused to gives Cybersecurity fundamentals to OT managers.</description></item><item><title>Facebook data breach: a danger for state officers</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/04/04/facebook-data-breach-a-danger-for-state-officers/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/04/04/facebook-data-breach-a-danger-for-state-officers/</guid><description>A few days ago the news broke about a Facebook data breach : 553 million user records that were exposed in 2019 are now circulating freely online. The story caused an uproar because the dataset, which used to be sold for money, is now freely accessible to anyone.</description></item><item><title>Secure critical infrastructure "by design" and "by default"</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/25/secure-critical-infrastructure-by-design-and-by-default/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/25/secure-critical-infrastructure-by-design-and-by-default/</guid><description>I was reflecting with friends and clients on a topic that concerns all of us: the security of connected devices. Whether you are a producer or a user, in private or corporate environments, no one is excluded.</description></item><item><title>Weak Passwords and Unauthorized Access</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/18/weak-passwords-and-unauthorized-access/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/18/weak-passwords-and-unauthorized-access/</guid><description>A few months ago, a new &amp;ldquo;collection&amp;rdquo; of data breaches began circulating: someone had taken the time to aggregate cleaned-up data from multiple past breaches into a single consolidated database.</description></item><item><title>Improvised vulnerability management</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/10/improvised-vulnerability-management/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/10/improvised-vulnerability-management/</guid><description>On March 3rd, the Italian CSIRT (Computer Security Incident Response Team) published a bulletin reporting the active exploitation of critical Microsoft Exchange vulnerabilities.
That was the moment when companies should have immediately triggered a risk assessment, followed by a business impact analysis and an actionable response plan.</description></item><item><title>Training in managing cyber attacks</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/03/training-in-managing-cyber-attacks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/03/03/training-in-managing-cyber-attacks/</guid><description>A cyber attack against a company can feel very similar to a terrorist attack. Shock, disbelief, fear, and confusion are common emotions in the first hours after the incident is discovered.</description></item><item><title>The dangers of losing a domain</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/02/24/the-dangers-of-losing-a-domain/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/02/24/the-dangers-of-losing-a-domain/</guid><description>The UK&amp;rsquo;s exit from the European Union provides an opportunity to reflect on our dependency on digital &amp;ldquo;assets&amp;rdquo; that we do not actually own but often take for granted. Examples include IP addresses, domain names, and third-party service accounts (Amazon, eBay, etc.</description></item><item><title>The importance of the CISO</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/02/19/the-importance-of-the-ciso/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/02/19/the-importance-of-the-ciso/</guid><description>In this particularly challenging period for companies, many long-ignored or underestimated information security issues are coming to light. Several accelerating factors have put corporate security under pressure; the most relevant include:</description></item><item><title>Crisis management</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/02/10/crisis-management/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/02/10/crisis-management/</guid><description>Note: This article was originally written a few months ago but never published. I&amp;rsquo;ve now revisited it, adding some updated reflections.
This period has taught us many lessons at different levels.</description></item><item><title>Top management security</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/01/25/top-management-security/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2021/01/25/top-management-security/</guid><description>The recent case of MyFreeCams gave me the perfect example to explain to top management why digital security of individuals should be addressed across all levels of an organization. Their data breach had both reputational and digital security impacts.</description></item><item><title>The Darwin's Law of Evolution for computers</title><link>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2017/10/09/the-darwins-law-of-evolution-for-computers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.adainese.it/blog/2017/10/09/the-darwins-law-of-evolution-for-computers/</guid><description>We&amp;rsquo;re leaving in the &amp;lsquo;hype&amp;rsquo; era, where everything is sold as the Holy Grail for a non-real problem. Let&amp;rsquo;s try to analyze things with a critical eye.
Pushed by a friend, who is writing a couple of very good posts I recommend, I&amp;rsquo;m now sharing my thoughts about automation, the future of network engineers, AI, and so on.</description></item></channel></rss>